<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Webascrazy</title>
    <link>https://webascrazy.net/tags/other.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Webascrazy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://webascrazy.net/tags/other.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcasts, that I listen to</title>
      <link>https://webascrazy.net/2017/03/04/podcasts-that-i-listen-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 15:39:40 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://webascrazy.net/2017/03/04/podcasts-that-i-listen-to/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I am listening to a lot of podcasts - usually while jogging, playing Playstation games, commuting, taking a longer walk. Couple of years ago I think I was able to listed to a podcast while programming - but now I find it difficult to focus on programming while still keeping track of what is going on in the podcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I am looking for in the podcasts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relaxed atmosphere with a large dose of wit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stick to the subject&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;great moderation (which makes a combination of both above possible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the podcasts that I am enjoying are about technology and science (economy, astronomy, and mixed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use &amp;ldquo;Overcast&amp;rdquo; application on my phone and &lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm&#34;&gt;https://overcast.fm&lt;/a&gt; website when listening on my laptop. After getting used to it first, now, I usually speed up the podcasts twice the speed to save some time, and to listen to more content within given time. It takes only a couple of days to get used to it - and it saves a lot of time. Overcast has the option to set the speed of playback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;list-of-my-favcorite-podcasts&#34;&gt;List of my favcorite podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/itunes790864884/daily-tech-news-show&#34;&gt;Daily Tech News Show&lt;/a&gt; with an amazing Tom Merritt (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/acedtect&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/acedtect&lt;/a&gt;) - daily update with most interesting news, usually focusing on one, most important topic. 45-60 minutes, with different people joining to comment on the presented news.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/itunes128859062/the-skeptics-guide-to-the-universe&#34;&gt;Sceptic&amp;rsquo;s Guide to the Universe, SGU&lt;/a&gt; - weekly science podcast, debunking fake science and myths. Each eposide consists of the main topic, and several, regular segments, like: &amp;ldquo;Who’s That Noisy&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;What’s the Word&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Science or Fiction&amp;rdquo; where cohosts are given three news and has to guess which are actual science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/itunes764921538/review-the-future&#34;&gt;Review the future&lt;/a&gt; - 45-minute long discussion focusing on future issues. Predictions, news, influence on our lives, technology and politics. Hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/perryjon&#34;&gt;Jon Perry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tedkupper&#34;&gt;Ted Kupper&lt;/a&gt;, futurists and artists from Los Angeles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/itunes152249110/radiolab&#34;&gt;RadioLab&lt;/a&gt; - hosted by the great &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rkrulwich&#34;&gt;Robert Krulwich&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JadAbumrad&#34;&gt;Jad Abumard&lt;/a&gt; with many interesting co-hosts and guests joining the show. Radiolab is a show about curiosity and science. Where sound illuminates ideas, and the boundaries blur between science, philosophy, and human experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/+DjLMCSoI0&#34;&gt;Clockwise&lt;/a&gt; - Four people, four topics, 30 minutes. Clockwise focusses on technology topcis, with commentary presented from different perspectives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;? Science Friday&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;podcasts-about-programming&#34;&gt;Podcasts about programming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/itunes427166321/programming-throwdown&#34;&gt;Programming Throwdown&lt;/a&gt; - ~70-minute long episodes focusing on different programing languages and frameworks - amazing source of knowledge in case you want to learn more about paradigms, tools, langauges, and approaches that are popular among programmers using languages that you do not know. Hosted by Patrick Wheeler and Jason Gauci.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/+FFX0gQ4KY&#34;&gt;Stack Overflow podcast&lt;/a&gt; - programming podcast hosted by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/spolsky&#34;&gt;Joel Spolsky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;podcasts-i-turn-on-sometimes&#34;&gt;Podcasts I turn on sometimes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/itunes842818711/a16z&#34;&gt;a16z&lt;/a&gt; - the name stands for Andreessen Horowitz, a Silicon Valley-based venture capital firm. This podcast discusses tech and culture trends, news, and the future &amp;ndash; especially as ‘software eats the world’. It features industry experts, business leaders, and other interesting thinkers and voices from around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/+JA3W37I&#34;&gt;Econtalk&lt;/a&gt; - economics-focused podcast hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/EconTalker&#34;&gt;Russel Roberts&lt;/a&gt;, often with great guests to discuss economics topics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://overcast.fm/itunes73329284/science-friday&#34;&gt;Science Friday&lt;/a&gt; - Covering the outer reaches of space to the tiniest microbes in our bodies, Science Friday is the source for entertaining and educational stories about science, technology, and other cool stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be updateing the list as soon as my preference change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to the new Webascrazy.net</title>
      <link>https://webascrazy.net/2016/12/08/welcome-to-the-new-webascrazy.net/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 18:58:22 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://webascrazy.net/2016/12/08/welcome-to-the-new-webascrazy.net/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the new version of webascrazy.net!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I started learning &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; earlier this year, I started exploring different tools built using Go. On of them was &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; a &amp;ldquo;Static Website Engine&amp;rdquo;. I decided to give it a try, review its source code - and hopefully soon, also contribute my changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is my first blog set up using a static website generator. It is hosted using &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several blogs I have started, using Wordpress, Drupal, Blogger.com, Evernote + postach.io, I feel that using a static website generator is like having everything under control. I am a developer, and I using markdown feel super natural, and I don&amp;rsquo;t have to leave my cave (Atom + iTerm apps on OSX) to write and publish the articles. It is simple, fast and you can influence every single aspect of it (like building a vanilla html + css website - but faster).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be publishing at least 1 article per week in 2017 - that is one of the new year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous version is still available here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://v1.webascrazy.net&#34;&gt;http://v1.webascrazy.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>